Guide to the Institute for European, Russian & Eurasian Studies records, 1964-1995 RG0102
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Institute for European, Russian and Eurasian Studies records
1964-1995
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0102
32 Linear Feet
Collection includes correspondence, "Current News" newsletter, Li Li-San papers, seminars, and photos.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the Institute for European, Russian & Eurasian Studies.
Historical or Biographical Note
The primary mission of the Institute for European, Russian and Eurasian Studies (IERES, or the Institute) is to promote and support scholarly research on Europe and Eurasia. The principal disciplines involved are political science, economics and history. Cross-disciplinary work is strongly encouraged. Members of the Institute develop and participate in scholarly seminars and colloquia, publish and otherwise communicate their research to peer academics in public settings and to various branches and agencies of the U.S. government.
Scholars draw on the massive holdings of the Library of Congress and National Archives and a number of academic, governmental and private institutional collections. The George Washington University is home to the Slavic, East European and Asian Reading Room, a special collection of reference works and periodicals unequaled in other academic institutions in the area, and to the National Security Archive, the world's largest private repository of declassified government documents.
The Institute's history reflects the changes in the global arena since the early 1960's. In the aftermath of the Second World War, American colleges and universities were sadly deficient in scholars trained to conduct research on the Soviet Union, Eastern Europe, China and East Asia generally. Thus, they were also weak in their ability to educate their students and the public at large or to advise government leaders on policy toward these emerging regimes.
The Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies was founded in 1961 to help fill these voids by promoting and supporting scholarly research, policy analysis and undergraduate and graduate-level teaching in Soviet, Central and East European and East Asian affairs. After the Cold War ended, the Institute changed its name to The Institute for European, Russian and Eurasian Studies, and the new Sigur Center for Asian Studies was established in the Elliott School for International Affairs. Today, the Institute fosters study of the dynamic regions of Europe and Eurasia, efforts to overcome the Cold War, and the continued legacies of the Cold War divisions in Europe.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include correspondence of Director Dr. Franz Michael; Current News and Li Li-San papers; correspondence, seminars, annual report, executive committee, individuals of Institute for European, Russian & Eurasian Studies; and Photos of Phi Beta Kappa plaque dedication.
Much of this material was transferred by Dr. Franz Michael, Richard Thornton, and Institute for European, Russian & Eurasian Studies.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Correspondence of Director Dr. Franz Michael; Current News and Li Li-San papers; Correspondence, seminars, annual report, executive committee, individuals; Photos of Phi Beta Kappa plaque dedication; and records.
OCLC#
711778681
Political science; Economics; Cold War; Phi Beta Kappa; Washington (D.C.); Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Michael, Franz H.; George Washington University. Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies; George Washington University; Elliott School of International Affairs; George Washington University. Institute for European, Russian, and Eurasian Studies
- Correspondence of Director Dr. Franz Michael, 1967-1978; RG0102 Series 1; 3 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of correspondence of Director Dr. Franz Michael. The materials range in date from 1967-78.
  - Correspondence M, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence N, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - N.Y. Times Editorial Reply and Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence P-Q, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wu, Yuan-Li, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Xenogogic, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wu, Chen-tsai, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - WSR Seminar on China, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence X-Y-Z, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Orchids, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lectures (completed), Correspondence regarding (2 folders), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence C, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence B, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence T, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sinha, Nirmal Chandra, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - PH.D. Students, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Public & International Affairs, School of, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence R, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Personal (FM), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Republican Study July 1976 Comm., 07/1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Succession Committee, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - FM - Reviews (Books, articles, etc.), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence W, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Trager, Frank, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Taiwan, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Social Science History Association, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Speeches and Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence S, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence F, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fifth International Conference on the Unity of the Sciences, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Committee on United States-China Relations, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Recommendations for Students, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence U-V, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Takase, Tamotsu, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Michael's Commitments, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence A, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence G, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Current News and Li Li-San papers, 1975-1995; RG0102 Series 2; 24 Linear feet
  This series consists of the publication Current News and the Li Li-San papers. The materials were donated by Richard Thornton, and range in date from 1975-95.
  - Current News, 01/1993 --08/1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 06/1975 --12/1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 01/1977 --06/1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 01/1979 --06/1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 07/1977 --12/1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 07/1978 --12/1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 01/1976 --06/1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 05/1994 --12/1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 07/1978 --12/1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 01/1980 --06/1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 07/1979 --12/1979 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 09/1993 --04/1994 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 07/1980 --12/1980 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 01/1978 --06/1978 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Current News, 01/1995 --08/1995 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Li Li-San Papers, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, seminars, annual report, executive committee, individuals, 1989-1996; RG0102 Series 3; 4.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 3, Box 2)
  This series consists of correspondence, seminars, annual report, executive committee,and individuals.
  This material ranges in date from 1989-96.
  - Incoming Correspondence [1/2], 1994 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming Correspondence [2/2], 1994 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Review of the Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies Appendix IV - Colloquia Schedules, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Review of the Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies Appendix III - Report on E.A. Grad and Undergrad Programs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Review of the Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Review of the Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies Appendix I - Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Review of the Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies Appendix II - Report on Rees Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters of Reference [1/2], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters of Reference [2/2], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing Faxes Folder II, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Folder III, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Incoming GW Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Incoming Correspondence Folder II, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Outgoing Faxes Folder I, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Folder II, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Folder I, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Folder II, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Senate Committee Hearing on Economic Reform in the FSU, 02/17/1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Incoming GW Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Outgoing GW Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Folder III, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hoffman Research Travel Grants, 1994 1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hoffman Seminar RSVPs, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - RSVPs for Hoffman Seminar, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hoffman Seminar, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hoffman, A. Michael, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Petrach, William Ukrainian Studies Endowment, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Update CVs, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - News and Noteworthy - Spring, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - REF Report and Proposal, 03/1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Research Enhancement Fund - Report on Activities, 1994 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Research Funding - Trends, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Roberts, Thomas H., Jr., undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Roberts Research Grants, 1994 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - IERES Advisory Board, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - USAID Program in NIS, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Slavic Language and Literature Department, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Misc. Seminars (Classes), 1994 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Scout Report (Internet), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Smith Richardson Foundation, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - MUCIA Meeting - Cannon/Kanevsky Proj., undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Millar Guggenheim Proposal, 10/1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Korea Information Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kennan Institute, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kanevsky, Vladimir, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Other Newsletters (samples), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newsletter Fall, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - NSF - General and SBER, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - NSF Fac. Early Career Development Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - National Security Education Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - National Research Council, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - National Grants Management Association, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Endowment for Humanities - NEH, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Japan Foundation, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Muskie Fellowship, 1995 1996 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies Resource Guide, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Institute for Study of World Politics, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Institute for International Education, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - IERES/REES Misc. Background Info, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - IERES/ESIA Memoranda, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - IERES Annual Report, 1994 1995 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Hoover Institution, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - GW Office of Fellowships and Graduate Student Support, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - GW University Faculty Fund and Dilthey Fellowships, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 09/1995 --08/1996 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Foundation Center, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Fundraising Resources, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Fundraising/Grants Workshops, etc., undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Funding sources - general (lists etc), undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Fund for Democracy and Development, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Foreign Travel per diems, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Ford Foundation - meeting notes, 11/1994 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Fagan, Bart (prospect), undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - ESIA LAN Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - By George!, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - The Welling Lecture Series, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Asahi Shumbun Foundation, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - AAASS, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Outgoing Correspondence - Linden, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Visiting Scholars (Rejections), undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Miscellaneous Info - Research Fellows, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - ACLS - Executive Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - AAASS - Council - General (old), undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - AAASS - Action Committee on the Future, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Roberts, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - FSU Conference, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - SSRC - Pan European WG, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - SSRC - The US Role, 11/05/1993 --11/06/1993 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Eurasia Foundation, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Russia Trip (Conference), 12/12/1996 --12/17/1996 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - FYI: Hoffman & Roberts, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Wilson Center Applications (from potential scholars), 1996 1997 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Trachtenberg Prize Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Hoffman (Funding) Current, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Lecture at Inter-Am Defense College, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Gelman Information Center, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Ruben Azizian, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Ye Ruan (Mr. Shi) Chinese Embassy, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - EU Scholar in Residence Proposal, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - WEFA - Board, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Faculty Senate, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Social Science Research Council, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - SSRC/ACLS Joint Committee on Soviet Union and Successor States, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - PPC: Editing, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Problems of Communism ME Sharpe, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Problems of Post-Communism - meeting, 01/31/1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Problems of Post-Communism, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Problems of Post-Communism vol. 1, no. 1 - Status Sheet, 02/1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Xu Kui Discussion, 10/09/1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Giulietto Chiesa, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Duffey, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Library Committee [1/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Library Committee [2/2], undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - REES Perestroika, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publication Offers, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Menges-Abalkin Proposal, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Organizations, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pankin, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - REES Self-Study, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - ROTOBO Conference, 09/21/1995 --09/22/1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - ROTOBO, 09/1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - ROTOBO, 10/1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Russian Junior Faculty, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Russian Parliament Delegation, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "The Russian Review", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Sabbatical Request, 1994 1995 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Salzburg Seminar, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Slavic Review, 1994 1995 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Social Legacy of Communism, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Vorobiev Project, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - University Research Committee, 1991 1992 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - University of Illinois Press, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - University Paper Series, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Steve Osagbue, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Trachtenberg, 1989 1991 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Thomas J. Richardson, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Oksana Baydina, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Sergei A. Belianev, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Wesley Fisher, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - F. Gunther Eyck, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Bob Huber, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Senator Tom Harkin, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Randy Blake, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Ben Burdetsky, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Itzhac David, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Ellen Carnaghan, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Coates (AVPAAR), undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Rod French, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Boris Grushin, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Dr. Gerard Janco - Adjunct, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - John Hibbits, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - John Hardt, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Michael Kim, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Mickey East, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Vladimir E. Lazarenko, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - IERES Exec. Com., 1993 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - IERES Exec. Com., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - IERES Exec. Com., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Executive Committee, 1994 1995 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - IERES Executive Committee Meeting, 11/07/1995 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - IERES Annual Report, 1991 1992 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Hinton Report, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - ISSS Faculty Meeting, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - IERES Advisory Board, 1994 1995 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - IERES Faculty Meeting, 10/13/1995 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - External Advisory Board - Reports, etc., 1996 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Irwin Price, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Hoffman Seminar, 03/1995 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Swafford Project - NCSEER, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Tropea, 1990 1991 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Paris Conference, 07/15/1994 --07/17/1994 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Tokyo Conference/Korea, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - IBS Training, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
- Photographs of Phi Beta Kappa plaque dedication, 1999; RG0102 Series 4; 0.25 Linear foot (Box 1)
  The series consists of five labelled photos (Peter Hill, President Trachtenberg, Jonathan Chaves, Fife and Drum Corps) of Phi Beta Kappa plaque dedication at 22nd and H Street.
  The material date from February 22, 1999.
  formerly ACC#829
  - Phi Beta Kappa plaque, 22nd and H Streets, NW, 02/22/1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Professor Peter Hill, 02/22/1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - President Stephen Joel Trachtenberg, 02/22/1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Professor Jonathan Chaves (former PBK president), 02/22/1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jim Hess, University Special Events Office with fife and drum corps, 02/22/1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Records, 1964-1992; RG0102 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains brochures, flyers, correspondence, memorandums, invitations, schedules, reports, and programs. They range in date from 1964 to 1992. The materials concern faculty, courses, Inter-University programs with American University, open house, Library access, seminars, conferences, the American Assembly, and the Mid-Atlantic Region of the Association for Asian Studies.
  - Sino-Soviet Studies, Institute for, 1964 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sino-Soviet Studies, Institute for Conferences, Seminars, Etc., 05/02/1968 --04/02/1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sino-Soviet Studies, Institute for Courses, 1967 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sino-Soviet Studies, Institute for Graduate Programs, 08/1962 --04/1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sino-Soviet Studies, Institute for Publications, 01/1964 --01/1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)